so this is the note on a toughie vichara
the first of the shorter notes sometimes
translated as unobtainable by reasoning
or not accessible to doubt but the
Cartesian kobito ergo zoom is also in a
sense inaccessible to jails where I
cannot doubt my existence without
tacitly assuming it this merely shows
however that one cannot get beyond the
cogito by doubting it the demo is beyond
the cogito the cogito then can be
reached by doubt one doubts and doubts
until one finds what one cannot doubt
what is inaccessible to doubt name the
attribute oh but the demo cannot be
reached this way
thus the demo the certainly inaccessible
to doubt is more than that is altogether
beyond the sphere of doubt the
rationalist however does not even reach
the inadequate kobito or if he does
reach it he overshoots the mark for he
starts from the axiom that everything
can be doubted including of course the
cogito so
what what what what is it exactly about
the demo that makes it beyond that doubt
because you know I can doubt what is
what is uh what are the five aggregates
what is the cause of suffering it seems
like I can doubt these things but then
here none of here is saying that know
the Dhamma is not something within that
sphere of doubtful thinking at all okay
what it means means that Dhamma goes
beyond that sphere as in even your
experience of doubt is within that
universal sphere the demos describe the
Dhamma describes and the reason why you
cannot doubt that universal sphere is
because that's what you are that is the
structure your experience that is your
experience so you can step back through
doubting only so far as goji torgussen
describes where you can then doubt well
where you cannot doubt the fact that you
doubt you can doubt the content of your
doubt but you cannot doubt the nature of
the doubt and that's what that way is
the nature of phenomena present being
that phenomena might be doubt might be a
feeling of happiness might be whatever
whatever has a nature to appear is can
be called phenomena so the Dhamma is not
concerned with the content of that
phenomena which is what you doubt it's
concerned with the nature which is what
you cannot doubt the nature of an a
reason thing that's why he said the
Buddha said how did he put it well I
don't know miss Perez but he the
targeted teaches the understanding and
freedom from well I am paraphrasing
obviously freedom from presently reason
things means means that things in the
utmost universal nature they can vary by
the content but what they cannot vary in
is the fact that they have a nature of
arising as in being manifested that's
what's in common to everything that you
experience is that it has a reason it
has presented itself and that's
something you cannot doubt why because
the doubt is it experience in itself
that shares the nature of being
in itself so that's why if somebody is
able to discern that you actually free
yourself from all the passion towards
the content aversion towards the content
of your experience hatred distraction
delusion doubt in itself as well you
cannot doubt the Dhamma then you can
doubt where you saw the things as an
experience of doubt but you cannot doubt
the nature of manifestation of that
experience so it's a completely the
opposite direction well it's not even
the obvious direction it's a vertical
direction as anivia will refer to it
that's why it's inaccessible by
reasoning because reasoning operates
linearly operates its space and time but
in order to operate your reasoning in
space the time the phenomenon of space
and time needs to be there present
manifested and that's where the dam of
pertains to understanding of that
structure not being concerned with the
content that's where the water would 7
he would this five aggregates for
example is a way of describing your
experience as a whole in the utmost
universal manner so that's what you
would say whatever whatever feeling
there is past future present unpleasant
Pleasant neutral big or small far or
near personal impersonal internal
external doesn't matter what matters is
a feeling is there hence the aggregate
of feeling is present and the same goes
for everything doesn't matter what what
perception is present whether it's blue
yellow white red past future present
mine not mine impersonal personal
doesn't matter the content of it what
matters is that the phenomenon of
perception is present the nature of
perception is there thus the aggregate
of the session perception is is
manifested so that's why the thinking
and again comes back to that negative
thinking we discussed in a previous
video that's where thinking needs to stop
that's where thinking needs to stop
being concerned with with a method and a
content in trying to figure it out on
that basis but start seeing the the
peripheral of your content that's how
you develop mindfulness as well
mindfulness to the extent necessary for
the final knowledge as into the
peripheral to the extent necessary to
actually discern the whole human
situation without resorting to greed
aversion delusion that arise as a result
of not understanding
whenever a doubt arises it always
presents itself as promising like you
know if addresses you towards the
content of your doubt it presses you to
clarify so that's what doubt is a
hindrance that pulls you that makes you
kind of revolve around it but failing to
see that it works like a trap it traps
you it hooks you and pulls you in and
you are being concerned with the content
of the doubt for the sake of dispelling
the doubt failing to see that the only
true way to dispel the doubt it is to
see the doubt as a phenomenon that has a
reason as an experience the manifest
pertains to the general nature of the
manifestation of experience as a whole
which means that you might doubt the
content but the experience of doubt is
present and you cannot doubt that and if
you overcome your emotionally charged
assumption in regard to the presence of
phenomena as in you you overcome your
your appropriation of it this is mine
then you won't be pulled into the
content of the doubt nor will you be
pulled in the content of your sensual
thoughts and I will be pulling to call
to the content of the verse if those
because you have actually understood the
structure of it and by doing so you
freed yourself from the humorous poison
in evident as the Buddha will describe
those those so a month trying
to first approach the suitcase or the
notes whatever they don't necessarily
have a wide range of you know
familiarity with all the terms and so
inevitably they'll be doubtful and
confused is what you're saying that they
shouldn't necessarily give in to that
kind of pressing need to solve the doubt
as opposed to just kind of including the
doubt and whatever they're thinking
eventually yes but initially the person
won't be able to help that that's the
manual of thinking but she's gonna be
unpleasant
constantly having doubts arise in
question your whole existence not just
your Scholastic point of view he's going
to be unpleasant but that's it it's a
necessary necessary thing to go through
then eventually of course when you start
discerning the nature of the present
phenomena it doesn't matter what it is
even if it's a doubt in itself you will
recognize that all you need to do is
stay on the other continue discerning
the extent of that presence of that
phenomena not being concerned with the
content of it and that's how you
overcome the hindrances as well and
that's the first jhana like if you fully
develop that kind of thinking that is
free from the pressure of the content of
sensuality five hindrances in general
that is the thinking and pondering of
the first jhana vitarka which are the
correct phenomenological thinking that
has no greed aversion delusion in that
they have been subdued beforehand the
same is coming overcoming the the
feather of doubt as well no doubt it's
more it's more fundamental in a sense of
like not even discerning the sphere of
the of the nature of the phenomenon so
that you have fettered by the doubt
there is a hindrance of the doubt like
when you doubt various things but the
factor of the doubt pertains to the
doubt in the dumb not knowing what the
Dhamma is the more fundamental in that
sense yes so so the burner obviously is
free from the fetter of the doubt but he
can still have be assailed by the
hindrance of the doubt in austen regard
to the fundamental aspects of the Dhamma
that he understood well in regards are
the things because doubt in itself it's
unpleasant that's what people don't like
that's what people give into it and try
to get rid of it through clarifying or
defining whatever they're doubting about
sometimes that that that is that is
necessary to degree you must not look
into what you're doubting but there is a
clear point where you can recognize when
that doubt becomes almost neurotic when
that doubt becomes sort of self
maintaining it's just there for the
purpose of the doubt it's not concerned
with any evidence of proof that you're
giving it is just not disappearing and
that's when you're acting out of your
doubt emotional like through through
emotional response not through like
trying to understand the nature that
there so that's something that you a person
so that's something that you a person
will need to be restrained in regard to
feeling it emotionally so it's the same
it's that same restraint that helps one
then overcome doubt eventually like do
it it's not just only like because if
you if you have no restraint if you're
not able to beat hold its standard out
and let it in do you you'll be giving
him whatever it arises that pressure
will never manifest you'll be pulled by
it it would pressure by it so that's
then you can't how can you then see the
universal nature of that phenomena
behind its content when you fully absorb
it the content right away you can't help
it
that's where the strength comes first
sealer comes first because it's the same
principle of sensuality in there will
you need to be able to allow it to rise
it as a thought and then recognize that
that's not essential it is it's you're
craving delight welcoming entertaining
that thought that's recent Charlotte is
but you will never be able to see that
for as long as you're not restrained
physically and verbally in regard
sensuality and your automatic response
to reason sensuality is giving it into
the pursuit of the content or in case
will will give in towards the denial of
the content you can then see the nature
behind that content the peripheral you